<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Man driven out of the earth and darkness, by the light, life, and mighty hand of God where in plain and simple truths are brought to light, that so the cause of stumbling may be taken from before the eyes of the rulars ... / written ... from their friend ... called of men Humphery Smith.</title>
            <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4068_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33842</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13577558</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13577558</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1049:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Man driven out of the earth and darkness, by the light, life, and mighty hand of God where in plain and simple truths are brought to light, that so the cause of stumbling may be taken from before the eyes of the rulars ... / written ... from their friend ... called of men Humphery Smith.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The 11th. month 1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MAN Driven out of the Earth and Darkneſs, By the Light, life, and mighty hand of God: Where in plain and ſimple truths are brought to light, that ſo the cauſe of ſtumbling may be taken from before the eyes of the Rulars, and all ſorts of profeſſors in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> that out of their minds, ſuch things may be removed which hinder them from the love of the truth, and that their underſtandings may be opened, and receive the truth which makes free and believe in the light.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſomething related of the wonderful power of God, in the work of redemption and reſtauration, with a plain ſelf denial by him that takes up the dayly Croſs.</p>
            <p>Written as a viſitation of free and tender love to the captivated ſeed of God in them, who to him are not yet reſtored, from their friend who is now a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers for the teſtimony of a pure conſcience, in this fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtincking, wicked, abominable Priſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Common Gole and houſe of Correction at
<hi>Wincheſter,</hi> called of men <hi>Humphery Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, in the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> month 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:100464:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100464:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Behold the Lord worketh wonderfully, every morning he bringeth his judgments to light, he hath brought me back from the grave and ſaved my ſoul from hell, and ſet my feet upon a Rock.</head>
            <p>THe living truth of the Lord God which he hath revealed in me, by the mighty operation of his word of life, which living eternal truth being my life and ſhall laſt for evermore, and be as a ſtandard of the moſt high lifted up to all the ſcattered weary ſoules, that they may flow unto it, and have it to be unto them a place of refuge &amp; defence, to fly unto in the day of diſtreſs, and by it come to be made free, and in it, worſhip the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh and feel it in the inward parts, according as the Lord requireth, by which truth man comes to be ſanctified; for the word that liveth and abideth for ever is truth, which comes to be ingrafted into them who believe in the light, and in it wait for the promiſe of the Father, even that ſpirit of truth which the world cannot receive, for they know it not, it being in Gods wiſdome hid from the wiſdome of the world, who know not him that may be felt after and found, who is neer unto every one of you, whoſe meaſure of light in you, is it you are all to know; by it to come to know the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal power and godhead as they did who had not Scriptures,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. For the light of Chriſt in you is that which is to give the knowledge of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. who hath aſuredly revealed his ſon in me, and led me in the ſtraight way to life eternal, and the injoyment of the truth which is immortal, the which being to me a pearl of great price, and more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then a thouſand Rivers of Oyle.</p>
            <p>And that none may be hindred from receiving of this which I have moſt aſſuredly found to be more excellent then the royalty of Diadems, or the excellency of the moſt pureſt Gold, or the moſt renownedſt glory, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or riches, that the natural eye can behold; and that all who breaths af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter divine refreſhings, and the reſt that never ſhall be ſhaken, and the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the covenant of life and peace, may come to be gathered into the one fold of bleſſed happineſs, and reſt upon the rock of ages, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more be moved henceforth and for ever.</p>
            <p>And that if poſſible all murmurings and reaſonings (concerning me or what <hi>I</hi> was) may be taken out of the minds of all people of all ſorts, and that all jelouſies, whiſperings, and heart burnings in the wrathful na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be paſſified and cooled with the overſpreading ſtremes of Gods free love, which truely is ſhed and groweth in my heart, and ſtremeth forth as a well-ſpring of life toward the ſeed that is yet oppreſſed in them, among whom ſometime I walked in darkneſs, and wallowed in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; &amp; afterwards ſtood up as a tall Cedar in the height of profeſſion, preaching great &amp; high things dayly unto others: where by the I was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired by many hundreds, who thereby came not to receive power, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their ſins, neither yet attain to that which the ſouls of many of the thirſted after, whom ſince I have often mourned over in pitty, and in the bowels of my fathers love to the ſeed in bondage in them, from <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100464:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom I have been long and far abſent in body.</p>
            <p>And that none of them by looking and wondring at me, or any thing tat hath befallen me may ſtumble thereby at the light or truth it ſelf, or be thereby kept from receiving the living truth, or from giving heed to that which all the wiſe maſter-builders refuſe; nor that they by looking at what I was, before I received and lived in the truth, and at that which juſtly came upon me for my former rebellion againſt the light, nor at the judgements of God that come upon me within or without, becauſe of my unwillingneſs to follow him who ſaid I am the light, follow me, and ſaid,
<hi>He that will not leave father and mother, wife and children, goods or lands for my ſake, is not worthy of me; and he that will not deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs and follow me, is not worthy of me:</hi> and what a croſs it was for me to leave what I did, let that of God (in all that then knew me) judge, but I ſay, that none of them who were Colonels, Captains, Juſtices, Profeſſors nor people, by looking out at any thing concerning me, may not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from receiving the truth, and ſo kept from that which is the way to the father, and the door to the reſt for evermore.</p>
            <p>Therefore hath it lay long, (of late years) and often upon me, and that from the hand of the Lord, to lay ſomething before your eyes (O ye rulers, profeſſors, and people of <hi>Herefordſhire</hi> and thereabout) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring thereby to remove any cauſe of ſtumbling, by reaſon of what I was, or of any falſe reports raiſed upon me, whereby the whole truth of God might be evil ſpoken of. And this have I waited long to declare among you, either in words, writing or print; though thereby ſhame might come upon my former courſe of life, when I lived in all manner of ſinne and iniquity,
[except it were actual adultery, fornication, and murther,] and though alſo hereby, contempt may come upon all that great profeſſion I was in, when I preached dayly in the Sinagogue, or upon all that I then ſpoke or preacht, out of the innocent life of God; or if hereby at preſent ſufter I reproch, (as it is like I may by many) yet the reproch of Chriſt is greater riches to me, then the treaſuer-glory and preferment of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And firſt concerning my call out of the world, or my going out from my houſe, countrey and outward imployment.</head>
               <p>The light of Chriſt which condemns the evil deeds, comes from him who calleth his out of the world, and from their imployments to follow him, who putteth forth his ſheep and thruſteth fourth labourers into the harveſt, and <hi>Abraham</hi> of whoſe ſeed I now am, went out of his countrey, and from his fathers houſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. and him God bleſſed and increaſed mightily, and the Lord alſo called, and thruſt forth me, who at laſt was obedient to the command of the God of
<hi>Abraham,</hi> and ever ſince his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence hath been with me, and his mighty hand of power hath preſerved me, and his bleſſings have I found, and the increaſings of God have I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, praiſes to the Lord God of life for evermore; who hath called me by his word of power through his grace, which did teach me to deny un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100464:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and worldly luſts, and to obey his bleſſed will, which was and is my ſanctification in Jeſus Chriſt, who did alſo call <hi>Matthew</hi> from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of cuſtome to follow him, and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> from their imployment of fiſhing, and made them fiſhers of men; and <hi>Paul</hi> alſo being called, left his imployment of rent-making (after a time) and was obedient to the heavenly viſion, and thoſe then became a wonder and a gazing ſtock to many, yet they continued on, travelling through many countries as I ſince have done preaching the word of God with boldneſs.</p>
               <p>And one of theſe men who were called from their outward imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſaid, every man wherein he is called there abide, and whereunto they were called they did abide, (and ſo do I) and when the Prieſts and Rulers would have ſtopt their mouthes by their commands, they ſaid whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be lawful to hearken unto God or man, judge ye, but theſe called Miniſters of Chriſt did not ſay, he that is a husbandman there abide, for
<hi>Noah</hi> was a husbandman yet a preacher of righteouſneſs, and
<hi>Eliſha</hi> a plowman, and <hi>Amos</hi> a herdman, neither did they ſay, he that is a fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man let him ſo abide; neither did Chriſt ſay, he that will be my diſciple muſt follow his outward imployment or trade, but he ſaid he that will not hate father and mother, brethren and ſiſters, wife and children, yea and his own life too, cannot be my Diſciple, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.20. and if not a Diſciple much leſs a Miniſter of his.</p>
               <p>But hereby neither Chriſt nor them Miniſters of his, neither, I did or do intend to draw or perſwade people to idleneſs, or open a door for any ſuch evil, (neither is there many who are called out of the worlds wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and required to leave their families and called to the miniſtry) but that hereby it may plainly appear, that the command and call of Chriſt, to his work and miniſtery is to be obeyed, though it be to the forſaking of houſe, goods, or lands: for a miniſter of his ſaid we have forſaken all, (and have not I done ſo) and unto them who had forſaken all, and unto all ſuch was promiſed a hundred fold, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17,
18, 19. And Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away before one jot or tittle of his word ſhall fail; and truely I have found his promiſe true, for a hundred times hundred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold have I already received, bleſſed be the Lord for ever.</p>
               <p>But how contrary it was to my own will to fulfil the will of the Lord, in leaving my imployment and outward buſineſs in the world, let all them judge with the light who knew my converſation therein, and ſaw my eagerneſs in the things of the world and contrivances therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond many men; my heart being ſet in the earthly things, being very fierce in labouring therein, for the getting and increaſing of the fruits of the earth, as though I would have laid up treaſure for many years which might have been good in its place, if my mind had been redeemed out of it and my heart from the covetouſneſs thereof; but I ſay again, it was much contrary to my ſtrong will, to leave theſe things and the love of them, and much more that might be named and be taken from it with a hundred fifty pound loſs, and expoſed to want, hardſhips, revilings, impriſonments, whippings, ſtonings and all manner of cruel tortour, that the ſons of men might have power to inflict upon my body, and for <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100464:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>me (that ruled over many, and was reſpected by many) to become a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant unto all, and counted the off-ſcouring of all, and be abuſed by any boy or the vileſt perſon I meet, and it was much contrary to my will, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe that glory, honour, and preferment of the world which was offered me by the rulers thereof, when I was beloved of them and hundreds more; and when I preached among them in the Pulpits dayly, and was then called of men, Maſter, like the hirelings of
<hi>England,</hi> who being in the curſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe from ſin, 2.
<hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. yet. I ſtill refuſed their unrighteous gain, and denyed all their gifts and rewards, for the Lord in his mercy kept me out of them temptations, though ſometimes ſome that were then neer friends unto me would have perſwaded me to have taken ſomething of what was offered as to live upon, but I durſt not, if I had wanted food or rayment; but anſwered one Juſtice who was propoſing me a free gift to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward maintenance, which might have been worth 100. <abbr>l.</abbr> a year or more ſeeing I left my imployment freely to preach dayly, but I ſay I anſwered, I ſhall rather go in Sheep skins, and Goat skins, and eat bread &amp; drink wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that little honeſt meek principal in me, which then kept me from that (and ſuch temptations) in due time led me to be ruler over much, which before I had not power over; therefore I ſay unto all, it is good to be faithful to the little meaſure of God in the conſcience.</p>
               <p>For when I was but young and voyd of the knowledge of God, or his way of holineſs, my mind ran much in the earth, with a covetous care how to gain the riches thereof; and even then did the hand or the Lord follow me, and his witneſs in me did ſo judge and condemne me night and day for my evil, that at laſt I was ſcarce able to do any thing in the earth or go upon it; and then waiting to ſee what the reaſon was, after many houres, I ſaw clearely if I would leave the wickedneſs of the world, and follow the Lord and truſt him, I might have peace, and if not, I was like to be cut off; and then I left ſome ſinnes, and reſolved to live more holy, and began to pray and read, and then I went to follow the Prieſts, not knowing that in me which I was to hear and follow, yet it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly led me out of ſome evil, and ſo into ſome peace, and then my heart was exalted in the earth, though I increaſed in a profeſſion.</p>
               <p>And when I was in the height of the worlds way and worſhip, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting riches to increaſe, even then in an unexpected time did the dread of the Lord fall upon me, and his wonderful mighty power wrought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly in me, to break me off from all my waies and ſeperate me from all the worſhip of the world, and gave me to ſee the abominations of all the prayers of the wicked, and the invalidity of all the worſhips of all mankind who are out of Gods Covenant, and the operations then upon me by the terrible hand of the Lord, and the ſtrivings that were in me can never be declared, and then did the Lord command me to follow him in obedience to his will, to declare againſt all unrighteouſneſs of men Which I ſaw in the light of life to be in Prieſts, Rulers, and people, and I then ſaw clearely in the eternal light and foreſight of God, the hardſhips, cruelties, whippings, impriſonments, and dungeon, and many ſuch things which ſince in part have been upon this body fulfilled as may be <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100464:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>read in ſeverall of my bookes, (read the true Rule) and at that time did the povverfull life of God, ſo much break through me, with ſuch unſpeakable love, that I was even willing to leave all and walk with God.</p>
               <p>But then contrary to <hi>Paul,</hi> I reaſoned with fleſh and blood, that I ſhould be eſteemed a madman, and that people vvould not beleeve me, and that I was not fit (&amp; many ſuch things) then the word of the Lord was ſpoken in me, ſaying vvho is it, that openeth the mouth, is it not I the Lord; then vvas my bowels even turned within me, with the conſtraining power of Gods eternall love, and I began to be vvilling but when that vvas a little over, The tempter being neer, I reaſoned concerning my wife and children, how they ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, and preſently the promiſe of the Lord was, that they ſhould be cared for, and his promiſe vvas to me that he who converteth ſouls to God, ſhould ſhine as the Starres for ever, and when I had received them vvords into me, I vvas overcome vvith the refreſhings of God, and at the preſent made vvilling to undergo all tribulations, if in my whole life, I did convert but one ſoul to God, ſeeing and feeling the redemption of one ſoul to be ſo pretious, the vvhich then grew ſo ſtrong in me, that I was ſcarce able to retain, from preſent actuall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God therein, but when I looked at my outvvard things and how firſt to ſettle that in order, then was I by temptations made afraid, that it vvas a deluſion, or ſomething of the Devil tanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as an Angel of light, and then between both, I was in much trouble and diſtreſſe, not knowing vvhat to do, having not then known any call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Quakers, nor any ſuch operations in any man in thoſe dayes, yet that could hardly prevail to make me beleeve it was a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: but at laſt, reaſoning about outvvard things, I then reſolved not to leave them, but to minde the things of the vvorld, and not obey that vvhich called me out of the world.</p>
               <p>And to write in ſhort, at laſt I did ſtrive and joyne withall the powers of darkneſſe that I could, and uſed all means poſſible to drive the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God from me, and the thoughts of him and his works out of my minde; but woo was me after for it, and it had been but juſt, if his Spirit had never ſtrived more with me, but left me to be cut off for ever, and to remain in the horrible pit of darkneſſe, (and ſurely it was for the good of others, that the Lord did ſpare me, ſome whereof may now with me rejoyce for evermore,)</p>
               <p>For when all was too little to overcome the mighty power of God in me, then did the love of the world prevail, and even thirſtings, for the love of it to come in to my heart, to drive out the love of God; at laſt, I with it againſt God prevailed, though the living power of God was ſo great, that the Devil the Fleſh, and the world, was ſcarce able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it for a time, and ſo I have ſeen, Children Wife, Farmes, and Oxen, to hinder from the Kingdom of God, but that which hindred moſt, was the love of outward goods, &amp; ſo it it was but juſt with God, to take that at the laſt out of the way; and if he had ſwept all <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100464:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>away in his Anger, as from <hi>Job,</hi> he had done me no wrong.</p>
               <p>But when I had thus, in a curſed manner overcome the ſtriving of the ſweet and lovely Spirit of Truth, yet was I not quiet, but much troubled, and in a ſad condition, which I was not able to hide from the vvorld, who ſaid, <hi>I</hi> was going mad, ſeeing me ſo changed into ſadneſſe, but of all this and much more, I durſt not then ſpeak a word to any creature.</p>
               <p>And now mark, vvhat for my rebellion did juſtly follow; My out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward goods which I then loved more then Chriſt, became as a prey, and a ſpoyle to unreaſonable men, and moſt unjuſtly on their parts, was I by them deprived of it, and the Lord alſo dryed up all my ſprings within, that ſuch a time after I knew that I was left without hope, being in the horrible pit of Darkneſſe from God, that I could neither pray nor beleeve, but reſolved that I was accurſed from God for ever, (and that vvhich diſobeyed was ſo,) and being in a ſad miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, reſolved to write a warning to all people, that they may take example by me, and never reſiſt the Spirit, as I had done, but before I could write, (ſinking down into the condemnation, without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring againſt God, knovving him to be juſt, if he caſt me into the nethermoſt hell for ever; the Lord had compaſſion on me, and lifted my ſoul out of the horrible pit, and ſtayed me vvith his hand for a time: yet aftervvards, his afflictions follovved me in judgements within, and much trouble in things vvithout, vvhich my heart vvas ſo upon, and yet for a long time I turned not unto the Lord that did ſmite, that his hand might make whole, though checks I had by his light, in my conſcience, but ſtrong vvas my vvill about it, until the fierce judgement of the Lord did often break forth upon me vvith much aſtoniſhment of heart, and horrible indignation not to be uttered, vvith teares as ſtreames of vvater from mine eyes night and day vvhen it came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, vvith tremblings &amp; breakings, vvhich broke the hardneſſe of my heart, and opened avvay to ſomething in me, vvhith then I dearly loved; but going out agin from that, I reaſoned about my outvvards, and not vvaiting to receive counſell from the Lord, I vvent unto a rich underſtanding man, in outvvard things, vvhom I loved, vvho may yet remember that I made my complaint unto, that I vvas not able any longer to abide in the vvay of the vvorld; vvhoſe counſell I then took and my ovvn vvill together, and ſo ſought to keep tvvo King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſometime longer, and therefore much trouble follovved me vvithin and vvaſting loſſe, ſhame and deſtruction upon things vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
               <p>But however I durſt do no leſſe then follow the Lord; and be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto him, whatever loſſe I ſuffered, or whatever ſhame or reproach I might undergoe, though often times I was afraid, that this power of God in me, would ſoon come to an end, or fail from me, and that then I might return to my outward Imployment with great ſhame and loſſe, and that then, inſtead of doing ſervice for God, I might bring a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon his Bleſſed Name, and my ſelf, thereby, be a hiſſing ſtock
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100464:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to all men, and they ſay I began to build and not able to finiſh, and this alſo kept me back very much; but ſuch was the everlaſting love of the Lord, who is known in the wayes of his judgments, that his hand was heavy upon me, and his judgments increaſed in me, that there was no way for me to eſcape, but I muſt be obedient and bow under it, or be cut off for every by it, ſo that my bowels were often pained in me, and it is like for many weeks had little ſleep or bodily reſt, and ſometimes knew not my wife and children, that I ſeeled and heard breath in the bed by me, but thought they were people that I ſhould not be with; and therefore one time after it was day, I was riſing and putting on my clothes in a ſober manner, and in meekneſs ſaid, ſurely I ſhould not be here, and my wife then laying hand on me, eaſily perſwaded me, but I ſaid, I know not who I am with, neither did I know her voyce at that time, and ſometime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having endured much, I told ſhe and my family (with heavineſs and tears) that I was not able to endure it any longer, and that I had abode with them in the way of the world, ſo long as poſſibly I could, and that I muſt give up my life to ſerve the Lord, deſiring them with tears to be content, and in what I could <hi>I</hi> ſhould be as careful for their good as ever I was, and this is true, and but little of what might be written.</p>
               <p>For another time formerly the light of Chriſt in me, (which then I knew not) did ſo condemne me, and judge and trouble me in ſecret, that it brought ſickneſs upon me, and thereby being weak expecting I ſhould die, I was then much troubled &amp; it lay much upon my conſcience at that time, that I had not in the time of my health gone to the ſteeple-houſe, and in the fear of the Lord warned all people to repent, and I was then much grieved becauſe I thought I ſhould die, and not firſt in that thing diſcharge my conſcience.</p>
               <p>And ſo though I might write much, by what is written may appear to the meek and ſober minded, that the Lord did not onely call, but alſo thruſt me forth of the world into his harveſt, and this was of God, and the operation of his powerful word which called me out of the world, and hundreds ſince by the word of his power through me have been gathered out of the way of the world, and received the earneſt of the reſt eternal, and many converted unto Cod, and wo be unto them vvho openly oppoſe me in this the Lords work I now am in, which he hath thus called me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and let none think that I did wilfully neglect my outward imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; neither let any one think that I left my family as not regarding them, nor that I ſtay much out of that countrey for any by end, for the words are true, a Prophet is not without honour, ſave in his own countrey and in his own houſe, and thoſe that did ſince ſeek to ſtop my mouth, did not well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning my publike preaching, and ſomething of what followed.</head>
               <p>That none may ſtumble thereat, and ſay we called Quakers are ſuch, who change from one thing to another, and ſo what we hold, nor to be regarded, but I ſay thoſe that have no changes, are not come into the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100464:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>fear of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.19. and the fear of the Lord is to depart from evil. and they that departeth from evil are become a prey, but ſuch were clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and changed from glory to glory, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. and grew in grace and knowledge in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and what I did or ſaid then, was in a great zeal and real intent to do good, neither did I covet mens ſilver for it, neither was it my end to make a gain thereby though much was free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered me more then I intend to make mention, though I received it not, ſo that therein I was not much found in covetouſneſs; but when judgment came upon me as before mentioned, I gave up that preaching and ſaid at the laſt meeting I had then, which was at Stoke-bliſs, that my mouth was ſtopt at that preſent, but if ever the Lord ſhould open my mouth again I ſhould preach indeed, and it is ſo, prayſes to the Lord for ever, who hath indeed opened my mouth, and ſince I was no longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and the living truth of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus Chriſt do I declare and bear teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to his name where ever I come as his ſpirit moveth me.</p>
               <p>And let none hereby think that I now glory in what was then my ſhame, for though I had a great zeal then for God, it being not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledge on the Croſs of Chriſt which crucifies to the world, and all its vain cuſtomes; the which croſs being then left behind, which is the power of God, ſo the love of the world which is enmity to God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in me and the root of iniquity not then removed out of my heart, therefore fruits of diſobedience in ſecret were ſtill brought forth, which the world took little notice of, but I had one neer me, which did let me ſee all that ever I did, and reproved me for vain glory, and having the praiſe of men and the love of the world, and ſo my preaching did not bring ſouls home to God, though I informed their minds of many things vvhich many ignorant people knevv not before, and ſo though much love vvas in many, yet this brought not forth fruits of obedience unto God, and ſo all came to little; for the people remained in their ſins and received not power to come out of it, neither came they out of the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and cuſtomes of the world, not to be ſeperated from the unclean, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r did they come to the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which purifies the heart ſtands in the pure conſcience and reſpects no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for unto that I was not then come my ſelf, and ſo their faith and mind was vain being then in our ſins.</p>
               <p>Therefore let none think that I now juſtifie any deceit, hypocriſie, or ſecret evil, that then was in me, or practiſed by me, for in the preſence of the Lord God, I do openly declare againſt it all, and that ſpirit that acted me therein, (but I own that ſimple thing, which then encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged me to do good, out of an honeſt intent, and that kept me out of covetouſneſs, and from receiving of gifts.) And I openly declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all cruel, unj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt and ungodly actions and words, and all that filth which I wallowed in, before I was a zealous profeſſor, as it is known to many ungodly perſons, how I was once as wicked as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny of them, whom I warn all to repent, otherwiſe they cannot eſcape the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hell.</p>
               <p>And I utterly deny and declare againſt that blindneſs and hypocriſie <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100464:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>I was in, when I followed the Chief Prieſt from one Idols Temple to another, who were chief in the Serpents wiſdom, deceiving me and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, and taught me that knowledge which came from the Devil, who ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall be as gods, knowing,</hi> Gen. 3.5. And in that knowledge, (in which every man is bruitiſh, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.14.) from them hirelings I increaſed, which puffeth up, and increaſed my ſorrow, as before was men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; for by that Serpents ſubtilty, which I learned from them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me, I fought againſt, and reſiſted that which was holy in me: Therefore I declare in the Name of the Lord God, that all the hireling Prieſts do more harm than good, and ſhall never bring people to receive the power of God, but lead them into ſubtilty, and further off from the knowledge of that of God in them, <hi>Romans</hi> 1.19. And as true as the Lord God liveth, upon their death-beds ſhall both Prieſts and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple witneſſe this to be true: And its alſo as true, that I write this without any prejudice to any of their perſons, but in love to all peoples ſouls do I warn all them hireling Prieſts in <hi>Herefordſhire</hi> and elſewhere, to leave deceiving the people, for abſolutely the people are deceived by them, and forced to maintain them too, who may be warned of them by what I have learned by experience from them, having tryed them and their wayes to the utmoſt, and have much experience of them more then many countrey people whoſe ſouls I truely love, and therefore this I write.</p>
               <p>And I declare againſt that which ruled in me in the time of ignorance and perverſeneſs, and acted me in cruelty or oppreſſion towards any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to wrong, defraud, or inſult over any one in tyranny, either by word or action, or wherein I abuſed or ſmote with envy (which is of the Devil) <hi>Either man or Beaſt,</hi> and that whereby I was led into any manner of hypocriſie or double-mindedneſs, or any manner of evil whatſoever which was unjuſt in the ſight of God, though not ſeen by man: or any ſecret evil that then lodged in the dark corners of the ſtony heart then in me, whereby any thing did ariſe in me or proceed from me which was contrary to the humble, meek, innocent, upright life of the Lamb of God, who is now come and hath taken away the ſin of the world, and is pure, humble, meek, and lowly, whoſe life and power of love conſtraineth me to declare openly againſt all that which vvas done or ſaid by me in envy, either openly or ſecretly againſt any creature, for there is nothing done in ſecret, that ſhall not be made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>And let all who knew me before (vvho are ſaying I was an honeſt man be warned of the like evill, and leave it, conſidering, that if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, for many did look upon me, to be either a godly or an honeſt man, yet am I made willing to let open ſhame come upon all that, vvhich then vvas in me contrary to the Righteouſneſſe of God, for he alone is to be exalted, and the tranſgreſſor is to be aſhamed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.3. And every mouth ſhall be ſtopt, and every one ſtand guilty before God, and the ſhame and nakedneſſe of all, both Prieſts, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100464:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and People, ſhall appear as much as mine, vvhen Gods vvitneſs in them ariſe, though they cover it for a time by deceitfull flateries, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing liberty, but are as deeply the ſervants of corruption as <hi>I</hi> vvas.</p>
               <p>And I do affirm in the preſence of the Lord God, that there are a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of profeſſors who follow Sermons, and have gathered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into outward Forms, vvho are grown up into a profeſſion, and knowledge in the Letter, vvho are further off the Life of God than the Publicans and Harlots, and are grown into pride, hypocriſie, ſecret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, arrogancy and covetouſneſs; and ſome of them for a time denied the Prieſts, and then for their own ends, got into their places, and ſo are more abominable than they, and the tree of Knowledge they feed upon, but the good ſavour of pure obedience unto God, in all ſelf-denial, they have caſt beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde their backs, and are become an ill ſavour among all men; and the Lord God vvill viſit them for theſe things, and in the Day of his fierce Wrath vvill all ſuch vvant a hiding-place; and vvhen the day of howling and aſtoniſhment come upon them, as it hath paſſed upon me, then ſhall they know that the ſinners in <hi>Sion</hi> ſhall be afraid, and horrible fearfulneſs ſhall ſurprize the hearts of the hypocrites, and then ſhall they finde that God vvill not be mocked, though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y deceive themſelves vvith vain hopes, vvhich ſhall periſh vvith all ſuch profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors if they repent not and ſtrip themſelves bare from all their falſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings, vvhich in the day of the Lord (vvhich
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey put afar oft) vvill certainly be all too narrovv: For, becauſe of the greatneſs of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, vvithout the povver that overcomes all ſin; therefore vvas the Wrath of God the more upon me, and I never came to receive pardon for ſin, nor povver over it, nor to receive th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Son of God, until his judgements had confounded all that Wiſdom, vvhich I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from and among the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſts and profeſſors. And this is abſolutely true, and may be a warning unto all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</p>
               <p>And all that is herein declared, of the Strivings in me, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God which came upon me, is very ſhort of what it was, Neither indeed, can it be ever declared, being then confounded both within and without: not having any man to be a director unto me, nor then to guide me in Go is wiſdome, neither did any man bring me into that condition, nor lead me through it, but even the Lord alone in whoſe judgements I now rejoyce for evermore; but this eſpecially, would I have all people that then knew me to conſider, that at that time, (when I was in diſtreſſe,) I knew not well what I ſhould do or ſpeak, among men, neither what I ſhould be, being become a fool for Chriſts ſake, and my wiſdome being confounded, and my underſtanding brought to nothing, <hi>Read,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1.9.
<hi>verſ.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>And ſo that was true, which I writ in that book in Anſwer to
<hi>Edmond Skip,</hi> wherein I ſaid that we were but in meaſure leaving of the world, and entering into a little of that which is Eternall, at which time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, I was brought to be ſilent from my publike preaching,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100464:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and waited on the Lord, vvith a few fooliſh contemptible ones in the eyes of the world, at which time having loſt my earthly wiſdome, and not received that meaſure of the pure wiſdome of God, (which ſince he hath given me) whereby to order all my vvords and actions, in pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and moderation, before the eyes of all people, and others alſo might then vvith me therein fall ſhort, whereby ſome to this day may ſtumble at the vvhole truth of God, looking at what hapned among us, in that time, when the judgements of God vvas often on us, (by which judgement, his Sion is now Redeemed, and ſo they looking at that, and vvatch ever ſince for evill may be kept thereby from receiving the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tryed Stone, which the wiſe Maſter builders alſo refuſe, though we now knovv, he is laid in Sion (redeemed with judgement, for a ſtone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence, even to both the houſes of Iſrael; But let all take heed, of ſtumbling at the ſtumbling ſtone, (the light of Chriſt,) for other cauſes of ſtumblings, Eſpecially by me, I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by endeavoured to remove out of the way, (and mindes) of all that are willing to receive the Truth, or beleeve in the Light. <hi>John</hi> 12.36.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Edmond Skipp,</hi> if ever he come again to that, vvhich con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced him of evil, and made him in publike deny his preaching for hire and tithes, though after he ſtarted aſide, and ſtumbled in the darke, before the Light of life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (which once he honeſtly deſired after) was ſprung up in him, to which light if he return, and love the witneſſe of God in him; which hath ever ſince ſtood a witneſſe for me, and have let him ſee his barrenneſſe, and without a true eternall reſt, and if he to that be obedient vvhich is manifeſt of God in him, and by it, be led into meekneſſe, and plainneſſe, without prejudice, he may come to receive the living Truth of Jeſus Chriſt, for which this day I ſuffer bonds, for I did never yet look upon him, to be ſo utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, as not poſſible to receive the faith that purifies the heart and reſpects no mans perſon, for truly my love hath been to the ſeed oppreſſed in him, though that which hath exerciſed him in raſhneſſe, (againſt the truth of God) <hi>I</hi> do deny for ever, and there is neither him, nor any Prieſt, Preacher, profeſſor, or profane, that can have any good ground or reaſon to envy me for declaring openly againſt all that in them which I declare againſt in my ſelf, when it ruled in me, when I was as they yet are.</p>
               <p>I being by ſeverall long unjuſt Impriſonments detained from liberty, to declare in words thoſe and other things, therefore for this very end, have <hi>I</hi> written this in ſhort, that Gods truth might ſtand clear, and not ſuffer in any thing done or ſaid by me, before Gods pure wiſdome was born up in me, and that alſo the ground of all other things againſt the truth (if occaſioned by me) may be removed out of the mindes of all that are willing to receive the truth if they knew it, for I would not if poſſible, that any thing whatſoever which concerned me, ſhould ſo remain in the minde of any one, as that thereby he ſhould be hindred <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100464:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>from receiving the living truth, which I have found ſo precious, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which none can be ſaved; and if by the appearing of the ſhame of my former nakedneſſe an inlet for the truth may be made into the mindes and hearts of any, therein will be my joy and the eternall comfort of all them, who by receiving, and ſanctification of the truth, and faithfulneſſe in the light, do come to reſt in the kingdom of joy, and eternall peace for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Thus at preſent, in tender love, to the ſoules of you Rulers and Profeſſors in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> to whom I ſay, beleeve in the Light, and minde Gods witneſſe in you, and be not rigid, bitter, nor perſecutors of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light, who by them in the dark, are called
<hi>Quakers,</hi> among whom I have choſen to ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, for Chriſts ſake, and whippings, long impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, and dungeon, and now in the houſe of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, all which declares me to be as you may read, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 6.3. to the 11. Who am a friend to the ſoules of all mankinde, a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, not by the will of men, to whom I am known, by the name,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Humphry Smith:</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Written upon</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 18th. <hi>and</hi> 19th. <hi>dayes of the</hi>
6th. <hi>Moneth</hi> 58.</date> 
                     <hi>being in outward bonds at</hi> Wincheſter.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Sons of God, and the Daughters of Men.</head>
               <p>VVEre it not the ſons of God, that looked upon the beauty of the daughters of men, and ſo took them to Wife, becauſe they were fair? And was it not even then, when that the Lord ſaid, <hi>My Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall not alway ſtrive?</hi> And is it not juſt for the Spirit to ceaſe ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, when way is given to the eye, to go forth from beholding the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God within, to look at the fairneſs of the daughters of men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and alſo to take that into the heart, and be married to that? And was it not ſuddenly after this, that the Lord reſolved to bring the flood upon them and their Wives? And were not theſe ſuddenly overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the deep Waters, who were before called the ſons of God? And did not they ſink in the deep under Gods wrath, and periſh with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100464:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>who before had felt the ſtrivings of his Spirit, which being loved, obeyed, and kept in, maketh ſons, and are not the ſons to keep faithful to the Maker, themſelves to be the Spouſe of Chriſt, who redeems out of the luſt, and ſo to know the Maker to be the husband, and they as chaſte wiſe Virgins feeling the oyl.</p>
               <p>And were it not thoſe that ſtood before the Throne in white (then not among the world in filth) who had not onely waſhed their Robes in the blood of the Lamb, but alſo kept themſelves from being defiled with Women? and did not that which beheld the fair daughters of men, let in that which defiled the ſons of God, and ſo grieved his Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and was not her firſt-born a Murtherer, who looked out at, and ſo let in that, which was fair, pleaſant and deſireable to that eye? and did not ſhe (who was deceived by that which was fair without) ſay of her firſt-born, <hi>I have gotten a man from the Lord?</hi> (it was from the Spirit) and was not he a Vagabond in the earth, from the preſence of God, that ſhe from the Lord had gotten? and are not they from the Lord, who are marrying and given in marriage, now the Son of Man (who is the Bridegroom) is coming to be revealed, with power and great glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, in his people that waited for him? and are not thoſe alſo to be ſwept away as they were, who thus before the flood cauſed the Spirit of God to ceaſe ſtriving? And did not Chriſt ſay, it ſhould be ſo <hi>at his coming, as in the dayes of Noah, eating and drinking, marrying, and giving in marriage?</hi> and is it not ſo? Have not ſome even felt his coming near unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m; and yet not keep in the fear until he was come, and revealed in power, through the death of that, which had power over him; from whence that went forth, which in the minde conceived a deſire to the other glory, and ſo let that in, which then took place in the heart, in ſtead of the glory of God, <hi>who will not give his glory to another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But do I forbid marriage? nay: <hi>Marriage is honourable;</hi> but that which maketh honourable, keepeth out that which doth defile; and that which maketh honourable, is Humility, walking with God, and is to go before, and keepeth to God, and they that are joyned to him are one Spirit; but that which leadeth from that which maketh honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is out of the marriage, in that which doth defile, and ſuch God will judge, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mn them by his witneſs in them, for ſhould not man firſt ſeek the Kingdom, and come into the dominion?</p>
               <p>Did not <hi>Adam</hi> know his Wife, and beget that in his own likeneſs, which murthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Righteous? and yet did not <hi>Enoch</hi> walk with God, and beget ſons and daugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers? but this becomes hid from them, who follow that which leads from the thing, which was to joyn them to God, to follow that which looks at the fair daughters of men, and ſo take them to Wife, and be married to that, and know that as the firſt
<hi>Adam</hi> did, who are his ſons in his likeneſs, to whom I ſay, (who after the manner of men have a Wife) that of late years they who are married are as if they were not, the Reſurrection, and the Life being come, and the things of this world paſſeth away: But woe to them, from whom that paſſeth <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100464:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>away which is not of the world, which once from God they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and ſtrived with, and in them who were once inlightned, and taſted of the heavenly gift, who may conſider, that thoſe who had Wives were not to come at them, (that they might be ſanctified) before they came near to hear the voice of the Lord, and the voice of the mighty thunderings was it that ſaid, <hi>The marriage of the Lamb is come.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke a great Myſtery concerning Chriſt and his Church.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="request">
               <p>And this thing I deſire of you in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> when you have read this Book, to let any other people have it to reade: And ſuch as deſire more, may ſpeak to <hi>Henry Bedford</hi> for them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
